A Guide to the Marion Fremont-Smith papers FA1898
Rockefeller Archive Center
Marion Fremont-Smith papers
1950s-2006
Rockefeller Archive Center
Fremont-Smith, Marion
FA1898
23.58 Cubic Feet 18 standard record storage boxes
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged materials are available at the discretion of RAC.
Arrangement
Original order, as received.
Arrangement
Original order, as received.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Marion Fremont-Smith papers were donated to RAC as unrestricted gift in 2022. Transfers of archival records began at that time, with additional accessions as necessary.
Biographical / Historical
Notable positions held by Marion Fremont-Smith throughout her distinguished career in law and the non-profit sector include but are not limited to:
Assistant Attorney General of Massachusetts, Director of the Division of Public Charities. Chair of the American Bar Associations' Committee on Exempt Organizations. Member of the IRS Commission and Advisory Group on Exempt Organizations. Director of the Council on Foundations. Director of the Independent Sector (IS). Trustee of the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace. Fellow of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences. Senior Research Fellow at the Hauser Center for Non-Profit Organizations (Harvard University).
Scope and Contents
The Marion Fremont-Smith papers document her career in the law and non-profit spaces, primarily including her activities leading the Advisory Committee on Public Charities, her Russell Sage Foundation research on charitable trusts and foundations which led to the publishing of her landmark work "Foundations and Government" in 1965, as well as her efforts as the Chair of the American Bar Association's Committee on Exempt Organizations.
Select files also document a variety of her work with Governance and Accountability of Non-Profit Organizations at the Hauser Center at Harvard, her leadership of the Council on Foundations, and the Indepedent Sector.
Philanthropy; Non-profit organizations
- Tax Exempt Organizations, Trusts, and Estate Planning Files, 1950s-1970s (Box 1)
- Duke, 1970s (Box 2)
- Task Force on Exempt Organizations (Box 2)
- Attorney General's Advisory Committee on Public Charities Files, 1960s (Box 2)
- Attorney General's Advisory Committee on Public Charities, 1990s (Box 5)
- Attorney General's Advisory Committee on Public Charities, 1990s (Box 11)
- Attorney General's Advisory Committee on Public Charities, 1970s-1980s (Box 12)
- Attorney General's Advisory Committee on Public Charities, 1980s-1990s (Box 13)
- Russell Sage Foundation - Charitable Trusts and Foundations Study Files, 1960s (Box 3, Box 4)
- Russell Sage Foundation - Charitable Trusts and Foundations Study Files, 1960s (Box 8)
- Russell Sage Foundation - Charitable Trusts and Foundations Study Files, 1950s-1960s (Box 9, Box 10)
- Hauser Center - Seminars on Emerging Issues in Philanthropy, 2000s (Box 5)
- Hauser Center - Seminar Files, 2000s (Box 6, Box 7)
- Urban Institute (UI) (Box 6)
- Tax Exempt Foundations Files, 2000s (Box 7)
- United States Senate - Finance Committee, 1970s-2000s (Box 7)
- United States Senate - Finance Committee, 1970s (Box 11)
- ABA Section of Taxation Committee - UBIT Working Group, 1980s (Box 11, Box 12)
- UBIT Working Group, 1980s (Box 14)
- Panel on the Non-Profit Sector - Advisory Committee on Self Regulation, 2006 (Box 13)
- IRS Exempt Organizations Advisory Group, 1980s (Box 14)
- Public Charities Correspondence, 1970s-1980s (Box 14)
- Panel on the Non-Profit Sector, 2006 (Box 14)
- Independent Sector (Box 14)
- ABA Section of Taxation-Exempt Organizations Committee, 1980s (Box 14)
- Charitable Solicitations and Regulation - Background and Working Files (Box 15, Box 16)
- 1969 Tax Bill (Box 17)
- Council on Foundations Conference, 1967 (Box 17)
- Philanthropy and the Business Corporation paper, 1960s (Box 17)
- Commission on Private Philanthropy and Public Needs (Filer Commission), 1973 (Box 17)
- Patman Treasury Report, 1960s (Box 17)
- AG Files (Box 18)
- Foundations and Government - Working Files, 1960s-1970s (Box 18)